I've been in Afghanistan for 21 years.
كنت في أفغانستان لواحد وعشرين عاما.
I work for the Red Cross
أعمل لصالح الصليب الأحمر
and I'm a physical therapist.
وأنا معالج بدني
My job is to make arms and legs --
عملي يتمثل في صنع سواعد وأرجل --
well it's not completely true.
حسنا ذلك ليس صحيح تماما.
We do more than that.
نقوم بأكثر من ذلك.
We provide the patients,
نمدّ المرضى وهم
the Afghan disabled,
المعاقين الأفغان
first with the physical rehabilitation
أولا بالتأهيل البدني
then with the social reintegration.
ثم بإعادة الاندماج الاجتماعي.
It's a very logical plan,
إنها خطة منطقية جدا
but it was not always like this.
لكنها لم تكن دوما كذلك.
For many years, we were just providing them
كنا لعدة سنوات فقط نزودهم
with artificial limbs.
بأطراف اصطناعية.
It took quite many years
تطلّبت عدة سنوات
for the program to become what it is now.
للبرنامج كي يصبح ما هو عليه الآن.
Today, I would like to tell you a story,
اليوم أود أن أروي لكم قصة،
the story of a big change,
قصة تغيير كبير
and the story of the people
وقصة الناس
who made this change possible.
الذين جعلوا هذا التغيير ممكنا.
I arrived in Afghanistan
جئت لأفغانستان
in 1990
في 1990
to work in a hospital
للعمل في مستشفى
for war victims.
لضحايا الحرب.
And then, not only for war victims,
ثم لم يكن لضحايا الحرب فقط
but it was for any kind of patient.
بل كان لأي نوع من المرضى.
I was also working
كنت أعمل أيضا
in the orthopedic center, we call it.
في مركز تقويم الاعضاء كما ندعوه.
This is the place where we make the legs.
هذا هو المكان الذي نصنع فيه الأرجل.
At that time
في ذلك الوقت
I found myself
وجدت نفسي
in a strange situation.
في وضعية غريبة.
I felt not quite ready
شعرت أنني لم أكن مستعدا تماما
for that job.
لذلك العمل.
There was so much to learn.
هناك الكثير جدا لتعلّمه.
There were so many things new to me.
كان هناك الكثير جدا من الأشياء الجديدة بالنسبة لي.
But it was a terrific job.
لكنه كان عملا رائعا.
But as soon as the fighting intensified,
لكن حالما اشتد القتال
the physical rehabilitation was suspended.
علُّق التأهيل البدني.
There were many other things to do.
كان هناك عديد الأشياء الأخرى لنقوم بها.
So the orthopedic center was closed
لذلك اُغلق مركز تقويم الأعضاء
because physical rehabilitation
لأن التأهيل البدني
was not considered a priority.
لم يعدَّ أولوية.
It was a strange sensation.
كان إحساسا غريبا.
Anyway, you know every time I make this speech --
على كل حال، تعلمون أنه في كل مرة أقوم بهذا الخطاب --
it's not the first time -- but it's an emotion.
ليست المرة الأولى -- لكنه عاطفة.
It's something that comes out from the past.
إنها شيئ يأتي من الماضي.
It's 21 years,
لقد مضت 21 سنة
but they are still all there.
لكنهم لا زالوا كلهم هناك.
Anyway, in 1992,
على كل حال، في 1992
the Mujahideen took all Afghanistan.
استحوذ المجاهدون على كل أفغانستان.
And the orthopedic center was closed.
واٌغلق مركز تقويم الأعضاء.
I was assigned to work for the homeless,
كُلفت بالعمل لصالح المشردين
for the internally displaced people.
والأشخاص النازحين .
But one day, something happened.
لكن في أحد الأيام حدث شيئ ما.
I was coming back
كنت عائدا
from a big food distribution in a mosque
من مركز توزيع كبير للطعام في مسجد
where tens and tens of people
حيث كان العشرات والعشرات من الناس
were squatting in terrible conditions.
مفترشين الأرض في ظروف فظيعة.
I wanted to go home. I was driving.
رغبت في الرجوع للبيت. كنت أقود.
You know, when you want to forget,
كما تعلمون عندما ترغب في النسيان
you don't want to see things,
لا تريد أن ترى الأشياء
so you just want to go to your room, to lock yourself inside
لذلك تريد فقط الذهاب لغرفتك لتحبس نفسك بالداخل
and say, "That's enough."
وتقول: "طفح الكيل."
A bomb fell not far from my car --
سقطت قنبلة على مقربة من سيارتي --
well, far enough, but big noise.
حسنا ليست على مقربة جدا ولكن هناك صخب كبير.
And everybody disappeared from the street.
واختفى كل شخص من الشارع.
The cars disappeared as well.
واختفت السيارات أيضا.
I ducked.
أخفضت رأسي
And only one figure
وهناك هيئة شخص واحد
remained in the middle of the road.
ظلت في منتصف الطريق.
It was a man in a wheelchair
كانت عبارة عن شخص في كرسي متحرك.
desperately trying to move away.
يحاول مستميتا الابتعاد.
Well I'm not a particularly brave person,
حسنا لست شخصا ذو شجاعة خاصة،
I have to confess it,
يجب الاعتراف بذلك
but I could not just ignore him.
لكنني لا أستطيع فقط تجاهله.
So I stopped the car
لذلك أوقفت السيارة
and I went to help.
وذهبت للمساعدة.
The man was without legs
كان الشخص مبتور الأرجل
and only with one arm.
ولديه ساعد واحد.
Behind him there was a child, his son,
كان وراءه طفل هو ولده
red in the face
ذو وجه أحمر
in an effort to push the father.
بعد بذل الجهد في دفع الأب.
So I took him into a safe place.
لذلك حملته لمكان آمن.
And I ask, "What are you doing out in the street
وسألت: "ماذا تفعل في الشارع
in this situation?"
في هذه الحالة؟"
"I work," he said.
قال: "إنني أعمل".
I wondered, what work?
استغربت، أي عمل؟
And then I ask an even more stupid question:
ثم طرحت سؤالا أكثر غباوة:
"Why don't you have the prostheses?
"لماذا ليس لديك أطراف اصطناعية؟"
Why don't you have the artificial legs?"
لماذا ليس لديك أرجل اصطناعية؟"
And he said, "The Red Cross has closed."
وقال: "لقد أقفل الصليب الأحمر."
Well without thinking, I told him
حسنا و دون تفكير قلت له:
"Come tomorrow.
"تعال غدا.
We will provide you with a pair of legs."
سنزودك بزوجين من الأرجل."
The man, his name was Mahmoud,
الرجل وإسمه محمود
and the child, whose name was Rafi, left.
والطفل وإسمه رافع غادرا.
And then I said, "Oh, my God. What did I say?
ثم قلت: "يا إلاهي. ماذا قلت؟
The center is closed,
المركز مقفل
no staff around.
لا يوجد موظفون.
Maybe the machinery is broken.
ربما الآلات معطلة.
Who is going to make the legs for him?"
من سيصنع له الأرجل؟"
So I hoped that he would not come.
لذلك أملت أنه لن يأتي.
This is the streets of Kabul
هذه هي شوارع كابول
in those days.
في تلك الأيام.
So I said, "Well I will give him some money."
لذلك قلت: "حسنا سأعطيه بعض المال."
And so the following day,
ولذلك في اليوم التالي
I went to the orthopedic center.
ذهبت لمركز تقويم الأعضاء.
And I spoke with a gatekeeper.
وتحدثت مع بواب.
I was ready to tell him,
كنت مستعدا لإخباره:
"Listen, if someone such-and-such comes tomorrow,
"اسمع إذا قدم فلان بالمواصفات التالية غدا
please tell him that it was a mistake.
أخبره أرجوك أن ذلك كان خطأ.
Nothing can be done.
لا يوجد شيئ لفعله.
Give him some money."
أعطه بعض المال."
But Mahmoud and his son were already there.
لكن محمود وولده كانا هناك بالفعل.
And they were not alone.
ولم يكونا بمفردهما.
There were 15, maybe 20, people like him waiting.
كان هناك 15، ربما 20 شخصا مثله ينتظرون.
And there was some staff too.
وكان هناك بعض الموظفين أيضا.
Among them there was my right-hand man,
كان من ضمنهم ساعدي الأيمن،
Najmuddin.
نجم الدين.
And the gatekeeper told me,
وأخبرني البواب:
"They come everyday to see if the center will open."
"يأتون كل يوم ليروا إذا كان المركز سيفتح."
I said, "No.
قلت: "كلا.
We have to go away. We cannot stay here."
يجب علينا أن نرحل. لا يمكننا البقاء هنا."
They were bombing -- not very close -- but you could hear the noise of the bombs.
كانوا يقصفون بالقنابل -- ليس قريبا جدا -- لكن يمكنك أن تسمع جعجعة القنابل.
So, "We cannot stay here, it's dangerous.
لذلك: "لا يمكننا البقاء هنا، إنه مكان خطير.
It's not a priority."
إنه ليس أولوية."
But Najmuddin told me, "Listen now, we're here."
لكن نجم الدين قال لي: "اسمع الآن، نحن هنا."
At least we can start repairing the prostheses, the broken prostheses of the people
على الأقل يمكننا البدء في تصليح الأطراف الاصطناعية، أطراف الأشخاص الاصطناعية المكسورة
and maybe try to do something
وربما البدء في القيام بشيء ما
for people like Mahmoud."
للأشخاص مثل محمود."
I said, "No, please. We cannot do that.
قلت: "كلا، من فضلكم. لا يمكننا القيام بذلك.
It's really dangerous.
ذلك خطير فعلا.
We have other things to do."
لدينا أشياء أخرى لنقوم بها."
But they insisted.
لكنهم أصروا.
When you have 20 people
إذا كان لديك 20 شخصا
in front of you, looking at you
أمامك ينظرون عليك
and you are the one who has to decide ...
وكنت الشخص الذي يجب أن يقرر ...
So we started doing some repairs.
لذلك بدأنا القيام ببعض الإصلاحات.
Also one of the physical therapists
أيضا أحد المؤهلين البدنيين
reported that Mahmoud
قال أن محمود
could be provided with a leg,
يمكن أن يُزود برجل
but not immediately.
لكن ليس على الفور.
The legs were swollen
كانت الرجلان متورمتان
and the knees were stiff,
والركبتان متيبستان
so he needed a long preparation.
لذلك احتاج لتحضيرات مطولة.
Believe me, I was worried
صدقوني كنت قلقا
because I was breaking the rules.
لأنني كنت أخرق القواعد.
I was doing something
كنت أقوم بشيء
that I was not supposed to do.
كان من المفترض أن لا أقوم به.
In the evening,
في المساء،
I went to speak with the bosses at the headquarters,
ذهبت للتكلم مع المديرين في المقرات التنفيذية
and I told them -- I lied --
وقلت لهم -- لقد كذبت --
I told them, "Listen, we are going to start
أخبرتهم: "اسمعوا نحن نبرمج أن نبدأ
a couple of hours per day,
ساعتان كل يوم
just a few repairs."
بعض الإصلاحات فقط."
Maybe some of them are here now.
ربما البعض منهم يتواجدون معنا هنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we started.
لذلك بدأنا
I was working, I was going everyday
كنت أعمل، كنت أذهب كل يوم
to work for the homeless.
للعمل لصالح المشردين.
And Najmuddin was staying there,
ونجم الدين كان قابعا هناك
doing everything and reporting on the patients.
قائما بكل شيء وكاتبا تقارير عن المرضى.
He was telling me, "Patients are coming."
كان يخبرني: "المرضى قادمون."
We knew that many more patients
علمنا أن العديد الكثير من المرضى
could not come, prevented by the fighting.
لم يستطعيون المجيء منعهم القتال.
But people were coming.
لكن الناس كانوا يأتون.
And Mahmoud was coming every day.
وكان محمود يأتي كل يوم.
And slowly, slowly
وتدريجيا
week after week
أسبوع يتلوه أسبوع
his legs were improving.
تحسنت رجلاه.
The stump or cast prosthesis was made,
صُنعت الأطراف الصناعية المعدنية أو الجبسية
and he was starting
وبدأ
the real physical rehabilitation.
التأهيل البدني الفعلي.
He was coming every day,
كان يأتي كل يوم
crossing the front line.
يقطع الخط الأمامي.
A couple of times I crossed the front line
عبرت مرتين الخط الأمامي
in the very place where Mahmoud and his son were crossing.
في عين المكان الذي كان يعبره محمود وإبنه.
I tell you, it was something so sinister
أقول لكم أنه كان شيئا سيئا جدا
that I was astonished he could do it every day.
إلى حد أنني كنت مندهشا لاستطاعته القيام بذلك كل يوم.
But finally, the great day arrived.
لكن أخيرا حل اليوم الموعود.
Mahmoud was going to be discharged
كان سيتحرر
with his new legs.
عبر هذان الرجلان الجديدان.
It was April, I remember,
كان في شهر أبريل حسب ما أتذكر
a very beautiful day.
يوما جميلا جدا.
April in Kabul is beautiful,
أبريل شهر جميل في كابول
full of roses, full of flowers.
مليئا بالورود ومليئا بالأزهار.
We could not possibly stay indoors,
ربما كنا غير قادرين على البقاء بالداخل
with all these sandbags at the windows.
مع كل أكياس الرمل على النوافذ.
Very sad, dark.
كان حزينا جدا وقاتما.
So we chose a small spot in the garden.
لذلك اخترنا بقعة صغيرة في الحديقة.
And Mahmoud put on his prostheses,
ولبس محمود أطرافه الاصطناعية
the other patients did the same,
وفعل المرضى الآخرون الشيء نفسه
and they started practicing
وبدأوا التمرن
for the last time before being discharged.
للمرة الأخيرة قبل تحررهم.
Suddenly, they started fighting.
فجأة، بدأوا العراك.
Two groups of Mujahideen started fighting.
بدأ مجموعتان من المجاهدين العراك.
We could hear in the air
نستطيع أن نسمع في الجو
the bullets passing.
مرور الرصاص.
So we dashed, all of us,
لذلك هرعنا كلنا
towards the shelter.
نحو الملجأ.
Mahmoud grabbed his son, I grabbed someone else.
مسك محمود إبنه للخلف ومسك شخصا آخر للخلف.
Everybody was grabbing something.
كان كل شخص يمسك بشيء للخلف.
And we ran.
وجرينا.
You know, 50 meters can be a long distance
كما تعلمون 50 مترا يمكن أن تكون مسافة طويلة
if you are totally exposed,
إذا كنت مكشوفا تماما.
but we managed to reach the shelter.
لكننا تمكنا من الوصول للملجأ.
Inside, all of us panting,
في الداخل، كنا جميعا نلهث،
I sat a moment and I heard Rafi telling his father,
جلست للحظة وسمعت رافع يخبر أباه:
"Father, you can run faster than me."
"تستطيع أن تعدو أسرع مني يا أبي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And Mahmoud, "Of course I can.
وقال محمود: "طبعا أستطيع."
I can run, and now you can go to school.
أستطيع العدو والآن يمكنك الذهاب إلى المدرسة.
No need of staying with me all the day
لا حاجة للبقاء معي طوال اليوم
pushing my wheelchair."
دافعا كرسيي المتحرك."
Later on, we took them home.
أخذناهم للبيت في وقت لاحق.
And I will never forget
ولن أنسى أبدا
Mahmoud and his son walking together
محمود وإبنه يمشون معا
pushing the empty wheelchair.
دافعين الكرسي المتحرك الفارغ.
And then I understood,
وعندئذ فهمت أن
physical rehabilitation is a priority.
التأهيل البدني أولوية.
Dignity cannot wait for better times.
لا يمكن للكرامة أن تنتظر لأوقات أفضل.
From that day on, we never closed a single day.
منذ ذلك اليوم فصاعدا لم نغلق ليوم واحد.
Well sometimes we were suspended for a few hours,
حسنا، في بعض الأحيان تم تعليق خدماتنا لبضع ساعات.
but we never, we never closed it again.
لكن لم نغلقه أبدا أبدا.
I met Mahmoud one year later.
قابلت محمود بعد سنة.
He was in good shape --
كان رشيق القوام --
a bit thinner.
أرفع بقليل.
He needed to change his prostheses --
كان يحتاج لتغيير أطرافه الاصطناعية --
a new pair of prostheses.
زوجان جديدان من الأطراف الاصطناعية.
I asked about his son.
سألت عن إبنه.
He told me, "He's at school. He'd doing quite well."
أخبرني: "إنه في المدرسة. آداؤه جيد جدا."
But I understood he wanted to tell me something.
لكن فهمت أنه يريد إخباري شيئا ما.
So I asked him, "What is that?"
لذلك سألته: "ما الأمر؟"
He was sweating.
كان يتعرق.
He was clearly embarrassed.
كان باديا عليه الحرج.
And he was standing in front of me,
وكان جالسا قبالتي،
his head down.
مطأطئ الرأس.
He said, "You have taught me to walk.
قال: "لقد علمتني المشي.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لك.
Now help me not to be a beggar anymore."
الآن ساعدني أن لا أكون متسولا بعد هذه اللحظة."
That was the job.
تمثل ذلك في العمل.
"My children are growing.
"أولادي يكبرون.
I feel ashamed.
أشعر بالخجل.
I don't want them to be teased at school
لا أريد أن يُسخروا منهم في المدرسة
by the other students."
من قبل التلاميذ الآخرين."
I said, "Okay."
قلت: "حسنا."
I thought, how much money do I have in my pocket?
فكرت في كم عندي من مال في جيبي؟
Just to give him some money.
فقط لأعطيه بعض المال.
It was the easiest way.
كانت أسهل طريقة.
He read my mind,
قرأ أفكاري
and he said, "I ask for a job."
وقال: "أريد عملا."
And then he added something
ثم أضاف شيئا
I will never forget for the rest of my life.
لن أنساه بقية حياتي.
He said, "I am a scrap of a man,
قال: "أنا بضع أشلاء رجل،
but if you help me,
لكن إذا ساعدتني
I'm ready to do anything,
فأنا مستعد لفعل أي شيء
even if I have to crawl on the ground."
حتى لو توجّب علي الزحف على الأرض."
And then he sat down.
ثم جلس.
I sat down too with goosebumps everywhere.
جلست أيضا وقشعريرة اجتاحت كل جسدي.
Legless, with only one arm,
مبتور الرجل وله ساعد واحد
illiterate,
وأميّ
unskilled --
ودون مهارات --
what job for him?
أية مهنة تناسبه؟
Najmuddin told me, "Well we have a vacancy
أخبرني نجم الدين: "حسنا لدينا وظيفة شاغرة
in the carpentry shop."
في متجر النجارة."
"What?" I said, "Stop."
قلت: "ماذا؟ توقف."
"Well yes, we need to increase the production of feet.
"حسنا نعم، نحتاج لزيادة إنتاج الأرجل.
We need to employ someone
نحتاج لتوظيف شخص ما
to glue and to screw the sole of the feet.
لإلصاق وتثبيت براغي نعل الرجل.
We need to increase the production."
يجب علينا زيادة الإنتاج."
"Excuse me?"
"أستسمحك المعذرة؟"
I could not believe.
لم أستطع التصديق.
And then he said,
ثم قال:
"No, we can modify the workbench
"كلا، يمكننا تغيير طاولة الحرفيين
maybe to put a special stool,
ربما لنضع آدة خاصة
a special anvil, special vice,
وسندان خاص وملزمة خاصة
and maybe an electric screwdriver."
وربما مفك براغي كهربائي."
I said, "Listen, it's insane.
قلت: "اسمع، ذلك جنون.
And it's even cruel to think of anything like this.
ومن الوحشية التفكير في شيء كهذا.
That's a production line and a very fast one.
ذلك خط إنتاج وسريع جدا أيضا.
It's cruel
من الوحشية
to offer him a job
أن نعرض عليه عملا
knowing that he's going to fail."
ونحن نعلم أنه سيفشل."
But with Najmuddin, we cannot discuss.
لكن لا يمكنني مناقشة نجم الدين.
So the only things I could manage to obtain
لذلك الأشياء الوحيدة التي تمكنت من الحصول عليها
was a kind of a compromise.
كانت نوعا من التسوية.
Only one week --
أسبوع واحد فقط --
one week try and not a single day more.
محاولة لمدة أسبوع واحد لا يفوق يوما آخر.
One week later,
بعد أسبوع،
Mahmoud was the fastest in the production line.
كان محمود الأسرع في خط الإنتاج.
I told Najmuddin, "That's a trick.
أخبرت نجم الدين: "تلك حيلة.
I can't believe it."
لا أستطيع تصديق ذلك."
The production was up 20 percent.
ارتفع الإنتاج بنسبة 20 بالمئة.
"It's a trick, it's a trick," I said.
قلت: "إنها حيلة، إنها حيلة."
And then I asked for verification.
ثم طلبت التثبت من ذلك.
It was true.
كان صائبا.
The comment of Najmuddin was Mahmoud has something to prove.
تعليق نجم الدين أن لدى محمود ما يثبته.
I understood
فهمت
that I was wrong again.
أنني كنت مخطئا مرة أخرى.
Mahmoud had looked taller.
بدا محمود أطول.
I remember him sitting behind the workbench smiling.
اتذكره جالسا يضحك وراء طاولة العمل.
He was a new man,
كان رجلا جديدا
taller again.
أطول مرة أخرى.
Of course, I understood
فهمت طبعا
that what made him stand tall --
أن ما جعله يبدو طويلا عندما يقف --
yeah they were the legs, thank you very much --
نعم، كان الرجلان، شكرا جزيلا لكم --
but as a first step,
لكن كخطوة أولى،
it was the dignity.
كانت الكرامة.
He has regained his full dignity
لقد استرجع كرامته كاملة
thanks to that job.
بفضل ذلك العمل.
So of course, I understood.
لذلك طبعا، فهمت.
And then we started a new policy --
ثم بدأنا سياسة جديدة --
a new policy completely different.
سياسة جديدة مختلفة تماما.
We decided to employ
قررنا أن نستخدم
as many disabled as possible
أكثر ما يمكن من المعوقين
to train them in any possible job.
لتدريبهم في أي عمل محتمل.
It became a policy of "positive discrimination,"
أصبحت سياسة "تمييز إيجابي."
we call it now.
نسميها الآن.
And you know what?
أتدرون ماذا؟
It's good for everybody.
إنه شيء جيد لكل شخص.
Everybody benefits from that --
كل شخص يستفيد من ذلك --
those employed, of course,
طبعا العاملون
because they get a job
لأنهم يحصلون على عمل
and dignity.
وكرامة.
But also for the newcomers.
لكن أيضا للقادمين الجدد.
They are 7,000 every year --
يبلغون ال 7,000 كل عام --
people coming for the first time.
الأشخاص الذين يأتون للمرة الأولى.
And you should see the faces of these people
ويجب أن تروا وجوه هؤلاء الأشخاص
when they realize that those assisting them are like them.
عندما يدركون أن أولائك الذين يساعدونهم هم مثلهم.
Sometimes you see them,
في بعض الأحيان عندما تراهم،
they look, "Oh."
يبدون متفاجئين.
And you see the faces.
ثم ترى الوجوه.
And then the surprise turns into hope.
ثم تتحول المفاجأة إلى أمل.
And it's easy for me as well to train someone
ومن السهل بالنسبة لي أيضا أن أدرب شخصا ما
who has already passed through the experience of disability.
خضع بالفعل لتجربة الإعاقة.
Poof, they learn much faster -- the motivation,
وسرعان ما يتعلمون -- الدافعية
the empathy they can establish with the patient
والتعاطف الذي يمكنهم أن ينشئوه مع المريض
is completely different, completely.
مختلف تمام الإختلاف.
Scraps of men do not exist.
لا توجد أشلاء رجل.
People like Mahmoud
الأشخاص مثل محمود
are agents of change.
هم عوامل تغيير.
And when you start changing, you cannot stop.
وعندما تبدأ في التغيير لا تستطيع التوقف.
So employing people, yes,
لذلك استمرينا في استخدام الناس
but also we started programming projects
لكن أيضا بدأنا برمجة مشاريع
of microfinance, education.
في التمويل الأصغر والتعليم.
And when you start, you cannot stop.
وعندما تبدأ لا يمكنك التوقف.
So you do vocational training,
لذلك تقوم بتدريب مهني
home education for those who cannot go to school.
وتعليم منزلي لأولائك الذين لا يستطيعون الذهاب للمدرسة.
Physical therapies can be done, not only in the orthopedic center,
العلاجات البدنية يمكن القيام بها ليس في مركز تقويم الأعضاء فقط
but also in the houses of the people.
بل أيضا في منازل الأشخاص.
There is always a better way to do things.
هناك دائما طريقة أفضل للقيام بالأشياء.
That's Najmuddin, the one with the white coat.
ذلك هو نجم الدين، الشخص ذو المعطف الأبيض.
Terrible Najmuddin, is that one.
ذلك هو نجم الدين الفظيع.
I have learned a lot
تعلمت الكثير
from people like Najmuddin, Mahmoud, Rafi.
من أشخاص كنجم الدين ومحمود ورافع.
They are my teachers.
إنهم أساتذتي.
I have a wish, a big wish,
لدي أمنية، أمنية كبيرة
that this way of working, this way of thinking,
وهي أن طريقة العمل هذه وطريقة التفكير هذه
is going to be implemented in other countries.
ستطبق في بلدان أخرى.
There are plenty of countries at war like Afghanistan.
هناك الكثير من البلدان التي فيها حروب مثل أفغانستان.
It is possible and it is not difficult.
ذلك ممكن وليس صعبا.
All we have to do
كل ما علينا فعله
is to listen to the people
هو الإصغاء للأشخاص
that we are supposed assist,
الذين من المفترض أن نساعدهم
to make them part
لجعلهم جزءا
of the decision-making process
من عملية اتخاذ القرار
and then, of course, to adapt.
ثم بالطبع ليتأقلموا.
This is my big wish.
هذه هي أمنيتي الكبيرة.
Well don't think that the changes in Afghanistan are over;
حسنا لا تحسبوا أن التحولات في أفغانستان انتهت؛
not at all. We are going on.
على الإطلاق. لا زلنا مستمرين.
Recently we have just started a program,
بدأنا مؤخرا برنامجا،
a sport program --
برنامجا رياضيا --
basketball for wheelchair users.
كرة السلة لمستعملي الكرسي المتحرك.
We transport the wheelchairs everywhere.
ننقل الكراسي المتحركة لكل مكان.
We have several teams in the main part of Afghanistan.
لدينا بعض الفرق في الجزء الرئيسي من أفغانستان.
At the beginning,
في البداية،
when Anajulina told me,
عندما أخبرني أناجولينا:
"We would like to start it,"
"نحب أن نبدأها."
I hesitated.
ترددتُ.
I said, "No," you can imagine.
قلت:"كلا." يمكنكم تخيل ذلك.
I said, "No, no, no, no, we can't."
قلت: "كلا وكلا وكلا وكلا، لا نستطيع."
And then I asked the usual question:
ثم طرحت السؤال المعتاد:
"Is it a priority?
"هل هي أولوية؟"
Is it really necessary?"
"هل هي ضرورية فعلا؟"
Well now you should see me.
حسنا الآن يجب عليك رؤيتي.
I never miss a single training session.
لم أفوت أبدا حصة تدريب واحدة.
The night before a match I'm very nervous.
أنا متوتر جدا في الليلة التي تسبق المباراة.
And you should see me during the match.
وينبغي عليك رؤيتي خلال المباراة.
I shout like a true Italian.
صرخت كإيطالي صرف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What's next? What is going to be the next change?
ما التالي؟ ما الذي سيكون التغيير التالي؟
Well I don't know yet,
حسنا لست أدري بعد،
but I'm sure Najmuddin and his friends,
لكن أنا متأكد أن نجم الدين وأصدقائه،
they have it already in mind.
لديهم فكرة عن ذلك في أذهانهم.
That was my story. Thank you very much.
كانت تلك قصتي. شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)